howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talked
about on the show we now have links to
books and articles referenced in recent
podcasts that are available on our
website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
ruts show com that's Jim ruts show com
today's guest is Jeff Gomez CEO of
starlight runner entertainment this is
gonna be a special show Jim because I'm
not nearly as sharp as some of your
other guests but thank you for having me
on yeah great to have you I don't don't
sell yourself short Jeff we've known
each other for I don't know here's a
while and you definitely got a lot to
add to the conversation thank you anyway
starlight runner is the world's leading
producer of transmedia entertainment
franchises and corporate narratives they
have worked with the top studio
executives and producers in Hollywood on
many of the most successful
entertainment brands extending them
across multiple media platforms some of
their projects have included Pirates of
the Caribbean
Star Wars men and black spider-man and
James Cameron's revolutionary film
avatar the Jeff could you give me an
example of where you did your magic on
one of these projects Wow is that all
know one of the preeminent was with with
something like Pirates of the Caribbean
where we are approached by the Disney
company because the first Pirates movie
did so well but it was an unexpected hit
and and the Disney Company wanted to do
sequels but weren't exactly sure how to
leverage the intellectual property
across all the different divisions of
the company they hadn't made very much
money in licensing and Merchandising the
original pirates movie they just weren't
ready for it so our job was to figure
out what made pirates so successful what
was the mechanism in the story besides
the movie stars of course that could be
leveraged across comic books and video
games and novels
the things that would allow for a Disney
to capitalize on the property and so our
magic was really to determine the
essence of what made the Pirates
universe special and to work with
divisions like Imagineering on the theme
park ride or their interactive division
on the massive multiplayer online game
to make sure that the essence of pirates
what made that movie so much fun was
infused into these different products
cool I had no idea that it was a
surprise hit because truthfully not
being a Pirates fan myself I haven't
really dug into it but my favorite
nephew swears it's the greatest series
in his lifetime and he's like wow and
he's like 33 34 years old right and he
goes it's the Lord of the Rings for my
generations way he describes it he knows
I'm a Lord of the Rings fanatic so it
couldn't get my tire praise on you know
the broader concept
well maintaining the integrity and
continuity of that rich universe as it
develops into all these different
spin-offs and product lines was our job
and we came to appreciate it the same
way he did it is kind of this epic
fantasy that deserves to be kind of
respected and and maintained you know
there's a sort of a side question but
just struck me how do you keep it from
getting cheesy or as I say in the series
TV world jumping the shark it's actually
very difficult because in Hollywood the
visionary is still the director perhaps
the the producer and and sometimes they
don't quite have their finger on what
exactly made these movies special so
sometimes we're allowed to kind of speak
truth to power and go you know this
screenplay doesn't quite nail it and
sometimes we're told to shut up and let
them do it and so we have watched
sequels to the works that we've worked
on maybe not be quite as good as the
previous one it's part of the job yeah
well those of us would go to movies a
lot know that happens all the time but
sometimes you get a you know
a big surprise like I still think
Terminator 2 is the greatest one in the
Terminator sequence sorry it's awesome
yeah in fact I'm gonna go watch it again
right before I go see the new Terminator
Jim I knew you were a nerd just not this
kind of nerd that's that's fantastic
I'm basically all kinds of nerd in fact
I think I'm gonna coin a new word Polly
nerdish ness I'm with you on the Polly
nerdish ness if I did a little research
before this episode one of the terms
that keeps popping up about you and your
company is transmedia storytelling could
you tell us what that is that's a fancy
term for you know being a nerd well
think about your experience of reading
Marvel or DC comic books how every so
often Iron Man can show up in
spider-man's comic book or spider-man
can team up with the Fantastic Four
those were were story worlds those
Marvel and DC comic book universes and
and in doing so there was a kind of
intertextuality there was the ability
for characters to visit one another and
still have a kind of persistent universe
going on there when I was young I wanted
this for the Godzilla movies I wanted
this for Planet of the Apes and and I
was often disappointed because the
licensing and Merchandising of these
properties was done in a kind of casual
fashion and nobody was interested in
making sure that Cornelius spoke in the
same manner in the comic books as he did
in the movies the Planet of the Apes
cartoon show had dinosaurs in it what a
dinosaur is really doing on the Planet
of the Apes
it's I couldn't deal that's because
those those worlds didn't have integrity
transmedia storytelling is the
methodology to take a story world and
disperse it across
media platforms in ways that allow for
it to retain a kind of canonicity
there's a continuity from one medium to
the next the quintessential transmedia
universe is Star Wars right now if you
read a Star Wars comic book it is in
Canon that's the official story an
official story set in the Star Wars
universe as are the novels the movies
the animated series and when you
assemble these pieces of the story world
they fit together sometimes almost
perfectly and that gives the fan
pleasure because everything that they
are countering everything they're paying
for counts as an addition to the story
world my job was to kind of introduce
this concept or help introduce this
concept to the Hollywood studios and the
big videogame companies as a method to
increase fan loyalty and sell more stuff
but also to create a kind of integrity
to these story worlds as massive
entertainment expressions almost like
artistic expressions if you will well
the world creation world builder
function is an artistic creation I'd
argue as someone who's fooled around a
little bit with building a few games
over the years the first thing I have to
do is a envision your world and either
greater or lesser detail it sounds like
transmedia storytelling starts with
building or extracting from a first
property a a world and then making it
rich enough that you can say whether X
is canon or not is that is that a
reasonable take I knew you were my kind
of guy chin rot yes and of course the
thing that I turned out the most on is
Lord of the Rings I've read the trilogy
37 times
holy mackerel and I'm getting ready to
read it for the 38th time the weird
thing is you get something new out of it
every time believe it or not but Tolkien
is real fans know spent many many years
decades
creating this world first before he
wrote the book right and in fact that's
correct
Lord of the Rings is embedded in a much
larger narrative simile and etc and some
other little bits and pieces and things
that were never published and so he's
you know invented languages invented
genealogies and it's all reasonably
consistent he in some sense he may might
be more or less the father of this
approach fairly close to it Jim I
actually am i started with Tolkien I
started with The Hobbit and The Lord of
the Rings and this was when I was very
young but old enough to understand that
everything I'd read up until that moment
felt like the author was just making up
a story with The Hobbit and Lord of the
Rings the richness of the characters
their histories their genealogies their
cultures mixed with this extraordinarily
passionate quest narrative that really
can touch your heart because of how
Frodo and his fellowship suffer and pull
so hard to to get this this job done
that combination of things felt
absolutely palpable and real to me and
and made me think I need to know how he
did this it was like a magic trick how
did you convince me that this fantasy
world is absolutely real as I'm
experiencing it on the page and that
started my own quest to understand the
engines of narratives how story is put
together across the world and throughout
history very interesting
if narrative is seems to be the base on
which you have built could you define
exactly what it is you mean when you say
narrative narrative the way we see it at
starlight Runner is slightly different
from story story concerns itself with
plot and theme and characters and so
forth but narratives to us is the
foundational structure of story these
are the elements that allow for the
story to unfold in any direction
backwards or forwards through time but
it also allows for the communication
between the audience and story you see I
already was kind of getting in touch
with with the 21st century way back in
1979 1980 and I came to understand that
the through the internet and my early
dabbling with it that the audience was
going to have a role in a narrative
structure that the narrative is going to
have to acknowledge the participation of
the audience if it's going to survive
into the 21st century
so narrative isn't just the structure of
story how story is built it also takes
into consideration the response and the
participation of the audience
so narrative is a river that we as
audience members are tributaries into
wow I love that I guess some of the
examples of that - Wayne as' first one I
remember I'm sure there must been
earlier ones was the whole phenomenon of
Trekkies and the conventions of Star
Trek fans etc and how that fed back into
the narrative I expect is that a good
example of that two-way nature it is
absolutely a great example and a kind of
foundational example I mean before Star
Trek we bought our Lone Ranger decoder
rings I mean maybe not me personally
that is even a little bit before my time
we could dress up as the shadow but with
with Star Trek there was so little of it
right and and we were so in love with it
that we began to to manufacture content
around it and mail it to it to one
another in through snail mail so these
are that's this is the beginning of
fanfic or fan fiction and and ultimately
these networks of fans who who somehow
got in touch with one another
somehow recognized that that we were
scattered across the United States began
to say you know what why don't we kind
of gather together to talk about this
and and those initials Star Trek
conventions in the very early 1970s were
the result and and that birth that the
first fandom but also kind of the first
truly transmedia effort perfect I still
remember how pissed off I was when they
cancelled Star Trek I go what the
the only TV show that's actually worth
watching and they can't what of course
you know because it was the first you
know there was no Jeff Gomez around in
those days and I'm sure you've read some
of the Star Trek spin-off novels and
stuff some of them really socked right
yes
but the maintenance of that passion
allowed for Star Trek to survive you
know six or seven very lonely years in
the wilderness until Star Wars ignited
this fan interest in cosmic space movies
and Star Wars of course was the first
but you better believe Paramount
Pictures ran into the studio and and
started shooting a Star Trek movie
to bring that back it wouldn't have done
that without the support of the fans
interesting what lacks I'm gonna just
throw in my little favorite topics and
I'm here before I move on to the next
topic which is Star Trek or Star Wars
what's what are you this is gonna touch
on some of the things we're going to be
talking about it cannot be
underestimated how deeply influential
Star Trek was for me I'm a Puerto Rican
kid in the projects and Lower East Side
in the late 1960s and this show came on
the air unlike almost any other show
depicting people who look like the
people around me people who had names
like mine
in space in the distant future you know
worthy of respect even worthy of being a
villain if you count Ricardo montalbán
as as calm absolutely you know
formidable formidable villain and you
mix that with concepts of like Spock's
logic or infinite diversity in infinite
combinations which i think is one of the
most wonderful story world philosophies
you could ever encounter and in all of
fiction that was was deeply meaningful
to me the fact that these characters
negotiated with their antagonists
instead of simply blasting them out of
the sky they did that once in a while -
it really really helped to to set my
frame of mind Star Wars was deeply
influential - but it's its simplicity
and it's the the polarity of the
franchise good and evil and and that
sort of thing as I grew older it it grew
a little too simple for me I do like
what they're they seem to be
experimenting with more recently in the
transmedia Star Wars franchise where the
force is really kind of this spectrum of
you know all kinds of behaviors and
attitudes and and and maybe they'll
resolve Star Wars in a way that makes it
a more interesting and collective kind
of property from now on I love your
analysis I mean I just tell people I'm a
Star Trek guy alright and I'll leave it
at that I do enjoy the Star Wars movies
I see them although I guess that was
that there was that one series with that
goofy character the the second trilogy
that sucked so bad I think I did not
watch the last of the three you're gonna
get nasty emails yeah that's that's Jar
Jar Binks I think each one
who came up with that all right I'm sure
that was that Jeff Gomez right well
there is a defensive charger but I don't
know if you want to get it
I've knock I don't quite go there
another little sidebar hadn't really
intended to ask this one I'm going to
anyway where do you think is the a
really rich fanfiction community that
let's say middle-class baby boomers and
Gen Xers probably don't even know about
what would you say is a great example of
that that's probably outside the view of
people like me there are fascinating
collectives of fanfiction it's
unbelievable what some people refer to
as boy bands bands like One Direction
have these ardent fan bases that have
written reams and reams I mean gigabytes
of fiction usually involving homosexual
relationships between band members or or
band members having relationships with
fans very self operatic epic storylines
involved with these kids as well as
things like kpop bands and and and and
so forth
that it's there's oceans of it in
television believe it or not
supernatural the CW television series
has a colossal amount of fanfic devoted
to those two brothers and their
adventures cool I had no idea I almost
never watched anything that has
advertising in it so I miss I try hard
to immunize myself against bad memes
being stuffed into my head so I tend to
miss things like network TV and yeah I
have to say my musical tastes don't
really go towards boy bands or kpop but
you know that's interesting hey that's
my job Jim that's my job and I have a
TiVo still a real live brand TiVo yep
the later me I'm a Roku guy and even
when I travel I carry my what I call my
traveling Roku in my gadget bag and I
can generally hook up my Roku up with
one of my little adapters to the hotel
TV and so I don't have to watch the
crapple and deal with their hideous user
interface see if I did that I'd never
get anything done goodness
another bit of terminology I saw
especially in the more recent materials
that I reviewed before the show is a
concept that you guys call collective
journey could you explain that gosh Jim
the the collective journey work is is
truly I thought the transmedia was going
to be kind of my signature work and Here
I am with collective journey and it's
it's something that's so exciting for me
back in the in the 1990s I was a video
game developer I had developed some
Nintendo 64 video games and a company
called acclaim entertainment approached
me about building a massively
multiplayer online game this was early
in that format and and so there wasn't
all that much to compare it to there was
ultimately know if you remember Ultima I
probably still have an account on that
yeah EverQuest Ultima all those are yes
sure so I looked at at those games I had
not been a part of that I did Dungeons &
Dragons so so we were telling stories
around the table there were tangible
little miniatures that you could move
about and and you can engage in in kind
of dramatic storytelling face to face
and and there was an emotional component
to tabletop gaming that I found missing
when when I went into the worlds of
Ultima and EverQuest in fact I noticed
that pretty soon after I showed up in
those worlds I'd get myself killed
you know and and I noticed that that was
a fairly pervasive problem so here you
are in a situation where there's an
opportunity to tell a massive collective
narrative where each participant could
somehow count for for moving the story
of this world law but what we were stuck
with due to all kinds of limitations but
I think predominantly a limitation of
imagination is the is the fact that you
were basically going to this fantasy
world to be a member of the audience if
you didn't get instantly killed all
you're really doing is kind of walking
around looking at things and hoping that
you can I don't know slaughter a monster
or something like that every once in a
long while a generation treasure it just
wasn't that satisfying it was a movie in
which we were all extras and and I
started to think about what what if
there were a way for for everyone to
have a rich story who was in that world
something that was meaningful and had
some kind of impact in that world well I
suggested this with some documentation
to acclaim entertainment and they told
me to go away because of course to do
that would have been to flip the table
upside down and start from scratch and
create an entirely new format for gaming
they weren't prepared to do that they
just wanted to do their ultimate game
that by the way never manifested after I
left it eventually shut down but I
thought about that for a long time then
as the years progressed and and I began
to notice how the internet was giving
fans a voice right so first in the 90s
if you had some kind of genre property
there was going to be fans to complain
about it and fans to adore it and fans
to argue over every aspect of it right
there was the bronze
Buffy the Vampire Slayer leave these
online message boards and things like
that message boards for Marvel and DC
Comics and that was interesting because
I was a part of a comic book company and
we would read those messages and we
would adjust the content in our comic
books at Valiant Comics that was really
interesting that was to me signified
that an individual fan somewhere could
voice their opinion and impact the
business plan the creative strategy of
an entire company little did I know that
that it would be just a few short years
later that many people would get
together and and voice their opinions
online and alter the course of the way
politics happen you know vote a black
man into the White House you know
generate an Arab Spring this is a method
that seemed to mystify all the people
around me but for me it was hey we're in
we're all in this massive multiplayer
online game and what we are doing and
saying count I don't have to be the
white Savior coming in to to kill the
villain grab the treasure and save my
community you know save the world I
could just have a voice that
collectively combines with other voices
and alters the course of the narrative I
didn't see a map for this in the Joseph
Campbell Ian hero's journey
Joseph Campbell mapped out this kind of
monomyth the story that all cultures
have told themselves from the dawn of
time back to Gilgamesh right I'm ever
there you go I read my Joseph Campbell
until I eventually threw it against the
wall because he had too much numerology
in it
yeah well all of that but but really I
mean I I have enormous respect for
Campbell and his research and really it
was my my quarrel isn't with Joseph
Campbell it was with the kind of
co-opting of the the hero's journey
narrative cycle those steps the call the
refusal of the call the mentor the
threshold guardian
you know the those standard beats that
you see in in every Hollywood movie
there was a kind of Hollywood ization of
the hero's journey that I progressively
got more and more uncomfortable with
especially with the rise of social media
and this global network of pervasive
communication why because the hero's
journey cycle emerged out of narratives
that made their cultures right okay so
there was it these are the stories of
rightness stories are built to teach us
right from from the dawn of time that's
the role of story and if we adhere to
that that's fine until Hollywood becomes
the epicenter of story then Hollywood's
version of right and wrong Hollywood's
version of the archetypal hero is going
to stand and be kind of you know
distributed to the entire planet and and
while that was fine for for some years
more recently the entire planet gained a
voice and the entire planet wants to see
itself in these movies and television
shows the entire planet wants to be sure
that we understand that heroes don't
have to have white skin and blonde hair
that certain very narrow depictions of
right and wrong are not necessarily the
whole world's interpretation of right
you know the American Way is is not the
entire planets way well we need to
understand how to tell stories in a
world where we now have global
television networks like Amazon and
Netflix this new modality of
storytelling collective journey the
observation that I'm making in response
to this kind of white savior hero's
journey narratives it's a great
transition point because I I noticed
again on your materials and as I was
doing some research that well the big
brands make the big bucks
you're also been working on applying
your techniques to education on
geopolitical causes they impact the
audience for this show is probably more
rich didn't those than they are in the
ins and outs of Hollywood sounds to me
like this collective journey idea of
yours is made to order for political
geopolitical educational applications
it's really where we began to hon it and
proved its efficacy yes and you're right
there's another aspect to what starlight
runner has done over the years that is
not very well discussed not not
publicized we don't seek too much
publicity around it and it is these
geopolitical transmedia population
activations could you tell us about some
of those at least one of those it's some
detail sure well the story is that we
were going about our business working on
projects like avatar and transformers
and so forth and it was shortly after
the election of Barack Obama that we got
a phone call from the Department of
Defense and I was like hello and and
they said listen the new administration
is studying various think tank files on
asymmetrical warfare it is a problem
that is you know is happening at
unprecedented level at this point and
president obama wants to wants to wrap
it up and extricate ourselves from this
kind of situation we're looking for ways
to to do that effectively and we came
upon this term transmedia when looking
through some materials from the Aspen
Institute
I said well who mentioned transmedia cuz
I certainly wasn't there and they said a
gentleman named Jordan green Hall a
friend of the Jim rut show I understand
yeah Jordan and I go way back right now
we've been co-conspirators and all kinds
of crazy stuff over the years so now it
all ties together see it this it becomes
a transmedia a story right now Jordan
was in the audience at MIT when I first
was talking about the efficacy of
participative narrative and transmedia
storytelling and he was fascinated with
it and wrote me and and we began this
correspondence and we eventually became
tremendous friends and and he kind of
helped me to start thinking about
applications of transmedia outside of
the conventional kind of nerd space and
and he was the one who had mentioned it
as a a possible application in
geopolitical situations of course the
first instinct for the government about
that was to weaponize it and that's what
I was confronted with which was very a
very sobering situation you know could
you imagine I'm Here I am playing with
transmedia storytelling and creating
entertainment with it and these guys are
saying well can transmedia be used in
the theater of combat and my response
actually Jim was that I wasn't
particularly interested in pursuing that
because in order to weaponize transmedia
storytelling you needed to remove
the component that made it transmedia
which or special which was authentic
dialogue a transparency and when you
remove that you get super propaganda you
get multilateral narrative which could
be used to ferment chaos and create
confusion amongst a population and that
didn't interest me at all
in fact I'd been observing that
methodology in Russia at the time and
thought that it was actually kind of
frightening to use story to confuse and
antagonize and exhaust an entire nation
of people so that you could assert
authoritarianism over them so I said no
I'm not interested and I said however I
do believe that you can use authentic
transmedia storytelling to get people to
organize themselves better and to pursue
progressive positive issues in a way
that could generate a significant
positive results and they said well
we'll pay you a lot less but let's let's
look into that shall we and and we did
an experiment in Afghanistan that
resulted in tapping into these these
towns in in Afghanistan tapping into an
ancient mythic kind of tradition where
if a stranger crosses into the town
they're protected no matter what
collectively the whole town has to get
together and stand up for that person so
so that person is safe so long as they
are in the town and that actually saved
some soldiers lives in Afghanistan there
was a Mark Wahlberg movie where where
there's a sequence where that that
actually happened it was a depiction of
an actual event so that was successful
and so we begin
working with the DoD and United States
Special Operations Command and and other
branches of intelligence - and the
military - to promote transmedia
population activation elsewhere in the
world interesting that's I'm gonna come
back to this and talk about Jordan and
some of the things he and I worked on
etc but I'm gonna pick up on the line
you just said about seeing what was
going on in Russia you know you're a
good guy but you know what about bad
guys using these same techniques how
would you suggest that people become
aware that these techniques exist and
can be used for evil and how do we
detect them and how do we fight against
them that's been really one of my major
concerns over the past a few years
because I'm extremely concerned about
the fact that techniques that were once
used to to generate joy and to to foment
a community fan communities and things
like that in some ways have been
corrupted and turned into scenarios that
are promoting extremism internal
conflict strife dividing and conquering
entire peoples and I think it's vital
that we recognize this what we have to
look for essentially is inauthentic
communication that's the bottom line
if story is coming at us in a fast and
furious way from a single source and
those stories have traits like like the
fact that they can contradict themselves
sometimes between morning noon and night
or they are divisive if they're deeply
negative if they're attacking if they're
laying claim to our darker impulses then
we would know that there is an
inauthentic behind their application
it's just not the way to
promote unity and a progressive
direction for society it's easy to say
that it's much more difficult to sell
tell somebody who's reacting to it and
lost in it and and actually is enjoying
it it's hard to tell that person you
know you're being gassed slighted or
you're allowing yourself to be
manipulated by false memes and this
invasion of divisive narratives
fortunately and and unfortunately I mean
your whole career is based on it right
we are suckers for narrative probably
going back to sitting around the
campfire in hunter-gatherer bands and
various people took their turns either
telling news stories or probably telling
the old classics with a few twists and
spins that have been passed down through
the generations for a thousand years and
so you know that's been a big part of
our conviviality at the level of the
small bands of humans and so we are good
at that we like that we're suckers for
it and so it can indeed be weaponized
you know you know you're describing all
these attributes two examples came to
mind like to get your reactions to both
of them
the first and perhaps the purest example
I would call the ban and Trump narrative
they talked to me about that a little
bit well it's chaos as a ladder in the
1990s a gentleman named Vladislav Surkov
a Russian ad agent a guy who was kind of
a failed science fiction author who was
in the advertising industry he visited
Paris France and was struck by an
avantgarde art movement that was going
on at the time essentially you entered
into the gallery and the gallery was
jammed with all kinds of pieces of
communication videos signs neon lights
and things like that and was all
flickering you and it was bombarding you
with a very provocative imagery
sometimes very enraging in imagery that
was racist material in there it
essentially was there to kind of
discombobulated you
and get you upset and and kind of keep
you on edge all the way through until by
the time you were done with the exhibit
you came out exhausted and and kind of
almost unmoored from reality he thought
that was fascinating and he went back to
the Russian Kremlin and said you know
you know we can use this you know we are
in a situation where glass gnost
is failing where the Russian economy is
on the verge of collapse where the
people are extremely restless and where
Vladimir Putin is not firmly gripping
onto power if we use these techniques we
can kind of freak out our own citizenry
and then assert an overriding theme that
of management that of the fact that
we're going to take care of things and
Jim here was the pattern see if you
recognize it these narratives began to
be communicated across Russian media and
of course because there is such a grasp
on on Russian media by the Russian
government it was a little easier even
than here but these kind of strange
contradictory narratives began to be
dispersed across Russia and at first
they seemed obviously fake it seemed to
the average Russian person that the
Kremlin were a bunch of clowns that that
they were behaving in bizarre and silly
ways then circle hired groups or
fermented fermented anti-muslim groups
to be on the rise anneal fascists and
things like that sometimes in ways that
actually allowed for them to clash in
the streets until the Russian police
forces descended on them and brought
them under control this seemed bizarre
and frightening to the Russian people
then the attitudes about the levels of
freedom or restrictions
it can we practice Orthodox Christianity
or Capri can we not all of these crazy
contradictory stories were bombarding
the Russian people so yeah at first they
laughed but then they got angry and then
they got exhausted and then within five
or six years they said you know what we
give up
just just manage it just take care of it
we we're withdrawing from this
conversation and Putin affirmed his
grasped the oligarchical Network settled
into power and Steve baton was studying
every step of this he he was a student
in essence of Surkov this is something
that worked that that Bannon understood
and certainly that our president fully
as a as a figure of the media fully and
deeply understands you think Trump
himself am I read could be entirely
wrong here is it Trump is some kind of
natural genius at rabble-rousing right
and he also has this amazing ability to
be completely unconnected to reality
like so as you were talking about people
that would say red in the morning and
blue in the afternoon Trump does that
with no psychological stress whatsoever
right five equals four four equals three
okay and he has this amazing talent and
then Bannon was the one who then
weaponized that with these insights
you're talking about and you know we
talked about Marxist Leninist am I kind
of think of the Trump administration as
banne inist trumpism right it's an
amalgam of trumps amazing idiot savant
abilities and sort of psychological
peculiarities plus bannon's insights
does that make any sense to you to a
degree certainly however you have to
believe that that there is some kind of
map of being followed by the President
himself whether a lot of it is intuitive
or not there is a specificity with
regard to the kinds of narratives he's
pursuing a specificity to the strategies
that he's running through that are
yielding fairly specific results and
seemed to be consciously directed now
again whether he's following some kind
of instruction book or intuiting them
himself I couldn't tell you but but the
the results speak for themselves
you're seeing him following the almost
the checklist that was developed by the
Russians that's interesting very
interesting it's not a it's not that
complicated
here we go to the weaponization here's
another one that fits the prototype that
was a very different constituency and
intent at least it strikes me as
following many of the things that you
that you enumerated and that's the
extinction rebellion yes
fascinating that's an example of a
spontaneous self organized social system
right it's it's transnational which i
think is fascinating
a lot of the ones that we followed thus
far have remained national around the
world and it's interesting that it
coalesced around a young girl a teenage
girl who found a very simple and direct
way of telling that story it it seems to
be building momentum based on the power
of narrative how easy it is to pick up
on and of course how easy it is for
people in this day and age to
participate in these kind of rivers of
narratives these kind of collective
journeys yeah and of course they also
you know they they're pressing the piano
keys for darkness very heavily right and
saying a lot of things that aren't true
that spin people up in terms of you know
the worlds that end in 12 years blahblah
right when and there
no nuance to the story at all it's it's
very pruned down to be easy to digest
press all the negative buttons one can
imagine etc well III think one can
account for the role of Malcolm X as
opposed to Martin Luther King there is a
kind of in some progressive movements
there is this kind of extreme end of it
that that does some of the
rabble-rousing and and does push things
forward even if it is sometimes
borderlines on violence or or violent
verbiage so you know we allow for for
some of that but yes there's been more
of this kind of extreme rhetoric around
the world which concerns me when it
comes to the rise in this kind of hyper
nationalism and authoritarianism
extincted rebellion just an example
someone has taken the template and
adapted it to a different domain and
what for at least partially a good
purpose right we do have to deal with
climate though yes you know most of
their prescriptions are non realistic
they terrify people there's a lot of
psychological research indicates that
paralyzing people with fear is not the
way to get people to take action it's
not and so you know they've essentially
taken the Russian playbook and adapted
it to another domain it may well be
doing more harm than good it's hard to
tell well I I'm looking forward to a
time where the world changes its
relationship with rhetoric because right
now there's a little too much of this
extreme application yeah that's
unfortunately you know we're suckers for
narrative but we are creatures of
language above all else right my own
field of cognitive science cognitive
neuroscience the main thing that
differentiates humans from chimps let's
say is language or the thing that's just
free language which is symbols and so
the idea that humans are not going to be
vulnerable to rhetoric that's pretty
hard to imagine let me ask you something
Jim and I've been curious about this it
seems to me
that right now infusing as much meaning
as possible into words has been to rigor
and we see this on the left and the
right we see this in students on college
campuses and things like that I've
wondered whether it would pay for us to
explore diffusing language altogether
and placing more distance between
ourselves and words and recognizing
words is just that things that have
potentially no power at all so that we
can get back to a level of decorum that
that could allow for a more even keeled
debate or a the ability not to be so
wounded and damaged by a rhetoric I get
scared sometimes because if mythology is
taught in school and and the students
tell the professor I'm gonna report you
because you just talked about a myth
where the gods are raping each other and
and so forth we could start to lose our
grip on understanding human nature and
literature and the arts and things like
that
yeah and it's happening you know you
know my take on it is that we're
becoming reach rival eyes right you have
these you know these factions like the
wokes who you know do the kinds of
things you just described we have the oh
right which have to have their own
rhetoric and stories and there's
fundamentalist religious people of three
or four different varieties and their
people are becoming more intensely
tribal and interrelated into a closed
model of discourse rather than having a
broad social model of this course in
which we can agree to disagree and do so
civilly so Jim I'm actually hoping that
this is a phase that we are all
experiencing because of the absolutely
free availability for us to express
ourselves anonymously or not
remember where I came from I came from
fandom Star Wars fans hated Star Trek
fans absolutely and in sports fandom
there are these terrific rivalries and
and and you can see fights and even
riots take place because you know fans
are on the sides of different sports
teams the reason those things could
happen the way they happen was because
the fans were allowed essentially to
network they were put in direct contact
with each other and so were given forums
to kind of advocate for their tribes
right now the entire planet has been
given the opportunity to do that and so
we are factionalized we are tribal izing
across all these different subjects and
so forth the reason I have some optimism
Jim is is because there are children who
are now growing up within this who are a
bit more chill because they've always
had a voice I'm talking about gen Z I'm
talking about kids 18 and under roughly
maybe 19 20 they've grown up with the
free and clear ability to just be on the
Internet
yes there's internet bullying and things
like that but generally they're freely
expressing themselves and don't seem to
have this level of avarice and and
selfishness and and tribalism amongst
them at least what we're observing and
we that's part of my job is to is to
watch these things so I'm hoping that as
these young people come into prominence
and start to help run the world that
we'll all get a little more chill so
interestingly you know you listen to
people like Jonathan hate and some of
the others who have been talking about
what's going on on college campuses the
reports back seemed to be that actually
it's getting worse on college campuses
that this woke phenomena is just
complete
really out of control um you know the
examples that you gave and that anything
this tribal ization is at least on
college campuses I can't say less for
the non college people which of course
people need to remember is two-thirds of
the country at least on college campuses
this pressure cooker of tribal ization
yeah and not just the wokes but also the
antelopes are also binding together with
you know becoming more and more
inflammatory etc so I'm not sure that
what we're seeing in the 18 to 21 year
old crew actually bears that out your
your point is well-taken I do think that
that there's a lot of steam being led
off in perhaps the wrong direction
because young people feel that they are
not able to assert as best they can
some national direction determine the
outcomes of major elections and so forth
and so the the small ponds becomes the
place where they are expressing their
anxieties but I also think that the
generation gap is pretty much the
largest one that we have ever seen in
the history of humanity so these kids
are communicating with one another and
super positioning themselves on the
Internet in in all of these interesting
and complex ways and they're professors
who maybe 10 or 20 years older than them
don't have access to any of that and and
have very little understanding for what
amounts to an entirely different way of
being with its own language with its own
cultures and this is creating a friction
in and of itself this isn't you know
some some hippy slang from the 1960s
this is an entirely different wave of
being and young people aren't being
taught that they're not being taught
media literacy in school so they're
having a difficult time reaching across
these divides to make connections with
older people and and
festers and and other authority figures
in the room are not attempting to much
to figure out why these kids think
believe and behave this way
they're just judging them and and that
creates more friction and of course
probably you know the nature of the
essentially the fractal ability to
organize at every level from the micro
to the macro makes us much more
confusing for the older folks you know
back to my day say you know nineteen in
the 60s we based had three factions the
jocks the hippies and the collegiates
right it wasn't that hard to figure out
what's of the three you were in and
maybe they were halfway in between I was
probably halfway between the hippies and
the collegiates right but you know it's
basically three big boxes today there's
a zillion levels at which people
identify and organize and it's
multi-dimensional intersectional etc so
it's a much more difficult cognitive map
for us poor old fogies to try to figure
out I'm gonna call you on the Star Trek
and and what I want you to think about
okay because it's easy to say are these
kids today but think about infinite
diversity in infinite combinations
that's in some ways that's happening
right now and if we step back far enough
and look at the expression and look at
their ways of communicating and look at
the fact that they are enjoying being
somewhere on various spectra or
spectrums that's beautiful in a way I
like the fact that that a child can can
walk into a school and say I'm as a it's
upsetting when they get angry with you
for forgetting that there is a or or
what-have-you but but isn't that
fascinating that that we have become
like the United Federation of Planets
just on planet earth and allowing for
that I can tell you both for firsthand
through close observation particularly
of this gen z cohort that that aspect
allows for liberation that aspect has
has helped them to reduce the kinds of
anxieties those of us particularly those
of us who were different in in some way
never got to experience in previous
generations so there there is some
something wonderful about what's what's
going on today yeah that want to make
clear I was not hacking on the kids
today you know I was actually trying to
make the distinction that the older
folks looking back at this fractal world
where everybody has a different way of
positioning themselves in many
dimensions is inherently a difficult gap
to transcend not to say that frankly I'm
with you I think probably these more
dimensions of freedom will end up good
though I suppose the one question mark I
might put on it is will we lose any
sense of social coherence and will our
society be strong enough to persevere
against challengers who are more
coherent than us wow that's fascinating
I'm a little bit optimistic I'm from New
York but I'm optimistic we're going to
get through this transition this
transition is bigger than the advent of
radio or television or any broadcast
medium when we were all sitting in front
of something and watching or listening
to it there were a very small number of
people who are establishing our reality
for us and there wasn't much choice in
terms of how we responded to that
reality maybe if a small percentage of
us rebelled against it another small
percentage of us as a kind of super took
advantage of it and became people who
took advantage in the system but by and
large there was this age of broadcast
that lasted for 150 180 years with the
advent of mass media now the printing
press and so forth
now we are in a new age Jim we're in the
age of pervasive communication and we
are attempting to find our footing and
and when everyone's a broadcaster things
are going to get messed up and things
are going to get confusing and people
you know have learned how to to try and
and fire cannons near the the
murmuration of birds you know to kind of
a try and push us in in certain
directions that's those those
multilateral stories like what happened
in Russia maybe what's happening here in
the United States today but we're going
to get a grip I believe we're going to
start to figure out what these
methodologies are and how to kind of you
know transcend them and and then our
diversity will become a strength I don't
believe that we're going to defuse
ourselves out of existence I think we're
going to be able to to get our act
together
I like it's a good thought you know
hopeful enlightenment view I would say
right think about you know who's our
global competitors for who will whose
model will dominate the future we have
the Chinese on one hand which is the
absolute opposite all right and then and
then we have the Russians which are
essentially chaotic and if we can
maintain a discipline but free
essentially the Enlightenment ideas
right we may be able to explore the
opportunity space better than any of the
people who are we are in competition
with but Jim in order to do that we
cannot submit ourselves to a a
multipolar world if nations like like
China and Russia become dominant if the
United States seeds power and influence
to those two poles then our voice
doesn't become the one that is the
shining beacon our voice becomes
sublimated to the cash that's coming at
us from China or the the power that's
coming at us from Russia and so we have
to be careful about remaining not just
great storytellers but aspirational
storytellers and aspirational people if
we start compromising and sublimating
ourselves to authoritarianism we're
gonna have major problems because then
who is there to be a role model for the
way the rest of the world behaves I
guess I'm not quite following lakitu I
mean what should we be looking out for
to do and to not do when we're in a
world in which you know our model or
let's call it the model which you very
eloquently described before or everybody
can find their own space in a high
dimensional universe versus other models
which are much more constrained could
you have imagined a world or a united
states where the NBA had to quell
people who were advocating for freedom
yeah it never would have been think
about just a few years ago I work in the
video game business Activision Blizzard
punished a player in its tournament for
advocating for a free Hong Kong
hopefully we're gonna get through this I
mean I think that the American people
should stand up and to start boycotting
any company that does that I know it's
those companies are very tempted to not
antagonize that you know billion person
market in China but that's a long way
off before they'll make any money there
they can lose their ass right now if all
decent Americans would say we're gonna
boycott anybody who plays that game who
tries to suppress free speech in
response to complaints from the Chinese
I'd like to see a mass movement start
where we just do not accept that from
our American company wouldn't it be
wonderful if that movement didn't have
to start because our leaders said that
is unacceptable
just as Americans that's that behavior
is unacceptable and told the NBA would
you stop that and so forth or or for
example the fact that so much of the
real estate in my city is is now owned
by a factions outside of this country
and and their influence their demands
some of which are unlawful some of which
are not in the interest of my city but
have to be acceded to because they own
huge numbers of blocks of real estate in
in my city
that's an insidious you know incursion
into our integrity
absolutely and unfortunately Real
Estate's a good one right because they
can't take it with them right they act
like a bunch of assholes we say go back
where you came from we're taking your
real estate you clowns right that's
something that people could do should
they get them self-sufficient organize
so I never bothers me and people say oh
yeah the Chinese are buying up this or
that well well they get too obnoxious
was kicking the hell out
take it back right but and yet that's
right now that would be incredibly
difficult to do because they they own so
much that to kick them out would mean
those buildings get emptied out well
who's gonna who's gonna pay those rents
who's going to own those massive
multimillion-dollar apartments and so
forth it would be easier to just kind of
quietly give them what they wanted which
corrupts our politics corrupts our civic
situation here and it's it's it can be
not that easy to do just to simply say
beat it yeah so so these are these are
forces that are pressing on us that if
our leadership is not holding to the
foundational values the American
narrative if that kind of collapses on
itself then we could easily be
overwhelmed by these techniques these
strategies these stringencies these
different ways of being that could cause
our fall and and those are things that
Jordan greenhalgh and Daniel Martin Berg
are really concerned about that I'm a
little bit apart of that group that that
has that concern about what direction
the world is going in yeah indeed let's
make that our last topic we'll talk a
little bit about game B mmm if you know
Jordan you know Daniel then you knew
about game be sure actually Jordan and I
and about 28 other people actually
cooked up game B back in 2013 and we
developed a fair amount of doctrine then
it didn't really seem to be going
anywhere and we all kind of went our way
and did our own little game via stuff or
not hmm
frankly I didn't mostly I worked on
other things but it seems like game B is
coming back again a surprising amount of
traffic on Twitter on Facebook etc and
for those listeners who don't know what
it is you can go check out the game B
group on Facebook or check out game B
all one word hashtag on Twitter and
you'll see a surprising amount of
traffic and essentially what game B is
is it's still a fairly hey
easy and rough attempt to define a new
social operating system for at least the
civilization and maybe for the world
that keeps us from committing ecocide
which we appear to be on you know
despite what I said about extinction
rebellion the basic idea is correct that
if we don't reform our ways we will
destroy our the carrying capacity of the
earth and there'll be a massive die-off
and we need to find new ways of being
that aren't I mean frankly these
jackasses that have these 22,000 square
foot town housing apartments in New York
they should really just be taken out
shot right or at least be nice put on a
barge and sent back from whence they
came and then fill those places full of
the homeless right nobody Hall most
people are the United States right no
reason we couldn't do that if we had the
will but that's just an example of some
radical thinking outside the box whole
idea of game B is let's start with a
blank sheet of paper no we want to avoid
ecocide and a major die-off and collapse
and and essentially we want to create
the operating system the values the way
we react with each other the ethos to
make a truly better world back to the
original game B we had a concept of we
say we want the game B world it's
basically it's to create a society
little you know this is I think very
simple but powerful that we would be
happy to live in ourselves truly happy
and proud to leave to our children I
don't think we can say either of those
things about our current world at least
most people can't and so we start with
that at this stage is still preliminary
but it struck me when I was doing my
research that you build imaginary world
yes some level that's that's your
superpower game B is in its own
struggling early partial kind of way
trying to think about what a new world
would look like of course we have the
constraint in the game B space that
we're operating in the real world right
when you're developing an imaginary
world for a movie you have a lot more
degrees of freedom but let's jam a bit
you know what are some things that
people should be thinking about
when we're designing designing is tube
stronger because it has that utopian
flavor you know just follow these
directions we know that's not the way
it's gonna be it's gonna unfold
organically in a network basis partially
and experimentally and evolutionarily
well advice would you give to the game
be world from your experience and
narrative around the collective journey
and even transmedia might be useful as
this community of people tries to invent
the future a better future than the road
we're on otherwise I certainly think a
game B is fascinating some of it floats
a little above my head at moments and
and the story sometimes is not quite
well told because you have all of these
extremely brilliant people talking to
each other about it and and the ability
to enroll people who may not quite be as
brilliant but still could have power and
influence that that hasn't quite gotten
there so the story needs to be told a
little better to start with in order for
greater influence and success to be
achieved but I do think Jim that it is
possible once we have a strong idea a
powerful foundational narrative to
execute the reason is that our
transmedia population activations didn't
stop in Afghanistan we've done these in
Mexico in Colombia in Canada and in
Australia and and for the most part they
have been remarkably successful when a
compelling story is combined with some
simple training the the media literacy
the ability to use social media to help
ferment social self-organization these
are can be good things and and can
result in a kind of spontaneous self
organized social system
that affects change that that can move a
whole societies in a positive direction
with Plan B one of the ideas that I
might contribute to to this besides
telling the story better and and
thinking about how that foundational
narrative can reach people you know
forming and galvanizing a foundational
narrative the other thing I think that's
necessary is for us to understand how
and why negativity can be so pervasive
and how to remove it from our lives I've
started examining the way that human
consciousness works and its relationship
to not just our lives and our past
traumas but to things like our five
senses particularly our eyesight can
things be done to wake us up to make us
use our brains more efficiently more
effectively Daniel does this with neuro
hacker those nootropic supplements that
he's developed and and those are
fantastic I take them those have helped
me think more clearly perhaps even
figure out ways to be a less negative
person and by negative I mean these kind
of strange defaults that exist since
childhood that says that I can't do
certain things rules that I set up for
myself that are almost arbitrary now
that I think about them if we can figure
out how to remove these negative
impulses from people then the
possibilities inherent and plan B become
easier to embrace develop and execute
interesting so yeah and part of the
great game B conversation there's a
tension between personal development I
guess I would describe it and building
institutions to help us be better people
sounds like your suggestion is to start
with the personal development side maybe
I think that's the easier of the two
because personal development it's easier
for me because I am the poster child for
how story can take someone from the
Lower East Side poverty the projects and
despite my last name you know achieve
you know a fair modicum of of success
and live a life that I could have only
dreamt about I couldn't even have
dreamed these experiences that I'm
having right now and that is because of
story and the impact of story maybe a
little bit of love here and there but
mostly story let's also be honest both
of us you know had interesting and
successful careers let's not let's also
not disregard the fact that we've also
had a lot of luck anything was no you
know and and it was a kind of fierce
determination a kind of street fighter
mentality that that caused me to figure
out things yeah the luck comes into play
but you make that luck because I fought
against myself I'm shy I had OCD all I
wanted to do was walk back and forth in
my bedroom so it was a real fight of
grappling with myself to push myself
into these social situations that
resulted in the luck of meeting certain
people are the opportunities that that
happens to come along so you know that's
a I try to teach young people about how
luck you know don't think about luck
because you've got to there's a lot of
work to be done
in order for what to come into play I
say the same thing you know if you push
against the world hard your share of
luck will probably come your way plus a
little bit but but the other part is you
have to be prepared and
fearless and courageous and go with it
right you know I still think about the
amazing bit of luck I had when I was 26
or 27 but it involved quitting my job my
wife and I both quitting our good jobs
moving to Boston and starting a company
with some guy with a story right and
most people thought we were nuts and we
did it and it was successful and that
you know change the complete reject eree
of our lives
because you know the luck was meeting
this guy at the right time in the right
place but the other part of it was being
you know decisive and courageous and
willing to follow that opportunity
that's right that's right any final
thoughts for the game be folks as they
continue to work together as a you know
ill-defined cloud of people to try to
define this future an aspect of game be
that I've heard about seems to center on
erecting new social media platforms and
other kinds of communication tools and
things like that and I've been more
someone to want to leverage the
platforms at hand when when starlight
runner goes to these movie studios or
video game companies and so forth the
first thing that we asked them is what
do you have access to for for the Walt
Disney Company it's everything you know
it already so that's the palette from
which we do our work so I would rather
game be be implemented across
established multiple media platforms
then take the time effort and massive
cost to invent the so-called trust
platform or some other kind of interface
or software that could make this thing
work I think a lot of the people of the
world want it to be better and and will
respond if the story is well told I
agree with you truthfully we tried to
build our own platform back in 2013 and
as you would have predicted it was a
whole lot of work and didn't get any
traction much easier to tell a better
story across the platforms that exists
the other
part that I push heavily is my doctrine
of weak links and strong links and that
is that no matter what platform you're
on most relationships in the online
world are inherently weak links
you know the people I know only through
the Internet are generally not people I
would ask to help me out if I got into a
jam or as I like to say you know a
friend is someone that will help you
move a real friend is somebody that'll
help you move a body I doubt you make
too many real friends on the internet so
I keep pushing and I think it's being
accepted in the game be world that we
need to build a tapestry that uses the
inexpensive wide-ranging weak links to
meet people but then to damn sure make
sure that when we can get together face
to face and also to build a real
face-to-face community where we live
because you know as Apes with clothes we
really are all about you know being with
other humans conviviality is the word I
think that's starting to be used in game
B to describe the fact that what really
rings our bell is being with our friends
or family you know having food and drink
and singing songs and clapping each
other on the back and telling jokes and
those kinds of things and I certainly
hope that as game B moves forward it
won't forget you know the real face to
face human stuff and over emphasize the
network stuff I'll agree with you Jim
don't underestimate the level of
intimacy and connection that that can be
possible with the technological
interface as we stumble past augmented
and virtual reality into scenarios where
we will in effect be able to look into
each other's eyes across great distances
I believe we can develop strong and
powerful relationships move the body
kind of relationships and again we're
seeing this with the youngest of the
prominent generations and if and when
that's possible it will be possible
to activate very large numbers of them
through a passionate storytelling and
and passionate requests for assistance
so that while you're seeing these
massive movements coalesce and form and
in some cases push things past the
tipping point to change you'll be able
to see them do this through work largely
online that can bring us closer to the
realization of Plan B just leave
yourself open to to that possibility
because it is it's something that's
fascinating that where we're seeing the
seeds of right now yeah that would be
interesting you know you probably don't
know this about me but I've been
involved with building our online world
since 1980 I went to work for the very
first company for the that was had a
consumer online service and so I've been
doing you know the many too many online
social media we'd call it now for almost
40 years and and yet and are there are
some cases where I have made some
relationships that are as good as the
real world but not that often but it
would be interesting if the new tools
and at some point they maybe there can
do that but so I guess I would amend my
statement a little bit use weak links to
reach lots of people but build the real
thing with strong links and today that's
mostly face-to-face but perhaps in the
future as our technology gets richer and
as you say something beyond augmented
reality maybe brain-to-brain networking
over time the ability to build strong
links could also move into the virtual
and we should be open to that and not
close our eyes to it I think it's not
too far off Jim that's great
I appreciate the consideration anyway
this has been wonderful you know Jeff
this was everything I would hope it
would be oh gosh absolutely rich and
fascinating and wonderful and that we've
covered a huge amount of ground and I'm
sure our audience will love it I look
forward to their feedback they can
connect with me through LinkedIn Jeff
Gomez through twitter at jeff underscore
gomez
remember the underscore because the
other Jeff Bowman is completely pissed
at me and Facebook it's Facebook /
transmedia but you'll find me if you
type in Jeff combs great well on that
note I'm gonna sign off and
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com
[Music]